Guide to the Physical Plant Department Records, 1953-1987. UA.10.05.0004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Physical Plant Department Records
1953-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Physical Plant Department
UA.10.05.0004
2 Linear Feet
The Physical Plant Department was responsible for maintenance, housekeeping, repairs, and other operations on the Duke University campus. The collection contains general materials concerning university services, facilities, properties and buildings, including floor plans, memos, bus schedules, photographs, reports, and departmental newsletters. It also contains files specific to the Duke University Marine Laboratory, particularly in regard to plans and blueprints for the building of the oceanographic research vessel "Eastward."
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Physical Plant Department Records were received by the Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, as a transfer in 1975, 1979, 1986, and 1999.
Historical Note
The Physical Plant Department was responsible for maintenance, repairs, and other operations on the Duke University Campus, including mail services, housekeeping, groundskeeping, energy conservation, and transportation. The Physical Plant Department was created between 1970 and 1972. It supplanted the Plant Engineering Department, which had replaced the Operations and Maintenance Department in the 1960s. The Physical Plant Department itself was supplanted in October 1987 by the Facilities Planning and Physical Plant Department, known later as the Facilities Management Department. In the early 1960s, Duke University Marine Laboratory established a new research and training program in biological oceanography and built a marine research vessel to facilitate the program. The vessel, equipment, and other program needs were financed with a grant from the National Science Foundation. The oceanography program was directed by Robert J. Menzies, and the research vessel planning committee was led by C.G. Bookhout, director of the Marine Laboratory. W.K. (Ken) Howard, Duke maintenance engineer, assisted Bookhout on the committee and corresponded directly with naval architects, shipbuilders, and engineers during the planning and construction of the research vessel. The vessel, “Eastward,” was completed around 1963.
Collection Overview
The collection includes files on buildings and operations related to the responsibilities of the Physical Plant Department. The General Records series contains bus schedules, floor plans, memoranda, photographs, newsletters, reports, inventories, appraisals and other materials concerning University buildings, property, and facilities. Files include materials on the heating plant, the Duke Homestead, the Duke Quarry, and “The Physical Plant Gazette,” a departmental newsletter.
The Marine Laboratory series contains a number of folded blueprints and plans for the oceanographic research vessel “Eastward,” as well as information about European shipbuilding companies; and memos, notes, reports, and correspondence related to the planning and construction of the vessel.
Related Materials
Building Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Marine Laboratory Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Facilities Management Department Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Physical Planning Department Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Oceanographic research ships--United States.; Duke University. Marine Laboratory; Duke Homestead (Durham, N.C.); Duke Quarry (Durham, N.C.); Eastward (Ship)
- General Records, 1960-1987; 1
  - Memoranda, 1973-1987 (Box 1)
  - Bus Schedule, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Report on Heating Facilities, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Coal Unloading Facility Steam Plant, 1975 (Box 1)
  - West Campus Steam Plant, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Major Repair and Rehabilitation, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Capital Improvements, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Budget Proposal, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Central Campus Heating Systems, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Safety Equipment, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Space Projections and Recommendations, 1961 (Box 1)
  - East Duke Building Photos, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Inventory Parlors - East Duke, 1960-1974 (Box 1)
  - East Duke Building, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
  - The Ark, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Music Building, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Womens College Library and Town Girls Room, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Duke Press, 1970, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin Auditorium, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Inventory - Duke Homestead - Photos, Clippings, Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Material Support (Box 1)
  - Panhellenic Council - Correspondence, Memos, Brochures and Clippings, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
  - Campus Center, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Bivins Building, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Carr Building (Box 1)
  - Branson Building, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Gym, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Prefab (Music) (Box 1)
  - Art Museum, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Art Building, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
  - Asbury, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Science Building (Box 1)
  - Buildings, General (West), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Womens College Library, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - West Duke Building, 1975 (Box 1)
  - The Physical Plant Gazette [Newsletter], 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Duke Quarry, 1974, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- Marine Laboratory, 1953-1963; 2
  - Oceanographic Vessel Specifications, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Blueprints, Sketches, etc., 1962 (Box 1)
  - European Ship Builders, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Virginia Fish Laboratory, 1955 (Box 1)
  - DX Navigator Instructions (Box 1)
  - Naval Architects, Sparkman and Stephens, 1962 (Box 1)
  - European Ship Builders, Norway, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Naval Architect - Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Rules and Regulations - Brochures, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Boat - Miscellaneous Information, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Engine and Auxiliary Information, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Typical Vessels, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Basic Plans and Specifications (Box 2)
  - Gear, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - Engine Information (Box 2)
  - Electronics and Navigational Gear (Box 2)
  - Research Vessel Operators Council WHOI, Woods Hole, MA, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Performance Data (Box 2)
  - Sturgeon Bay Shipbuilders (Box 2)
  - Notes (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Proposals and Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Brochure - Kelvin Hughes Unit Radar System (Box 2)